In the last video, we talked
在上一节视频中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
about the Gaussian distribution. In
我们谈到了高斯分布
this video lets apply that
在本节视频中
to develop an anomaly detection algorithm.
我将应用高斯分布开发异常检测算法
Let's say that we have an
假如说我们有一个无标签的训练集
unlabeled training set of M
共有 m 个训练样本
examples, and each of
并且
these examples is going to
这里的训练集里的每一个样本
be a feature in Rn so
都是 n 维的特征
your training set could be,
因此你的训练集应该是
feature vectors from the last
它可以是来自上一个这些特征向量的集合
M aircraft engines being manufactured.
比如 m 个飞机引擎产品的样本
Or it could be features from m
或者是
users or something else.
来自 m 个用户或者其它的什么东西
The way we are going to address
现在
anomaly detection, is we are
我们解决异常检测的方法是
going to model p of x
我们要从数据中
from the data sets.
建立一个 p(x) 概率模型
We're going to try to figure out what are high probability features, what
我们要尝试计算出这些哪些特征出现的概率比较高
are lower probability types of features.
哪些特征的概率较低
So, x is a
因此
vector and what we
x 是一个向量
are going to do is model p of
我们要做的事情是
x, as probability of x1,
建立一个 p(x) 的模型 表示 x1 的概率
that is of the first component
这是 x 的第一个组成部分
of x, times the probability
并用它乘以 x2 的概率
of x2, that is the probability
这是第二个特征的概率
of the second feature, times the
然后再乘以
probability of the third
第三个特征的概率
feature, and so on up
一直这样下去
to the probability of the final feature
直到最后一个特征
of Xn.
特征 xn
Now I'm leaving space here cause I'll fill in something in a minute.
这里我先空着 最后再来填满
So, how do we
那么
model each of these terms,
我们如何为这些项进行建模呢？
p of X1, p of X2, and so on.
p(x1) p(x2) 等等
What we're going to do,
我们下面要做的
is assume that the feature,
是假定特征 x1
X1, is distributed according
其分布
to a Gaussian distribution, with
服从高斯正态分布
some mean, which you
你也可以
want to write as mu1 and
写出期望 μ1
some variance, which I'm going
以及方差
to write as sigma squared 1,
我用 σ1 的平方表示
and so p of X1 is
这样
going to be a Gaussian
p(x1) 就可以写成
probability distribution, with mean
这样一个高斯分布
mu1 and variance sigma squared 1.
其期望为 μ1 方差为 (σ1)^2
And similarly I'm
同样地
going to assume that X2
我假设 x2
is distributed, Gaussian,
也服从高斯分布
that's what this little tilda stands for,
这里的小波浪线读作"服从"
that means distributed Gaussian
表示它服从高斯分布
with mean mu2 and Sigma
其期望为 μ2
squared 2, so it's distributed according
方差为 (σ2)^2
to a different Gaussian, which has
所以它服从的高斯分布与刚刚那个不同
a different set of parameters, mu2 sigma square 2.
它的期望和方差都不一样
And similarly, you know,
与此类似
X3 is yet another
x3 服从另外一个高斯分布
Gaussian, so this
因此
can have a different mean and
x3 也会有一个不同的期望
a different standard deviation than the
以及一个与其它特征不同的标准差
other features, and so on, up to XN.
直到 xn 都是如此
And so that's my model.
这就是我要说的模型
Just as a side comment for
顺便说一下
those of you that are experts in
对那些擅长统计的同学来说
statistics, it turns out that
实际上
this equation that I just
我刚刚写的式子
wrote out actually corresponds to an
写出来实际上就对应于
independence assumption on the
一个从 x1 到 xn 上的独立的假设
values of the features x1 through xn.
But in practice it turns out
但实际中 结果是
that the algorithm of this fragment, it works just fine,
这些算法的效果都还不错
whether or not these features are
无论这些特征
anywhere close to independent and
是否独立
even if independence assumption doesn't
即使这个独立的假设不成立
hold true this algorithm works just fine.
这个算法的效果也还不错
But in case you don't know
如果你不知道
those terms I just used independence assumptions and so on,
我刚刚提到的独立假说和其它相关内容
don't worry about it.
也不要担心
You'll be able to understand
你将会慢慢有能力去理解
it and implement this algorithm just fine
并且能很好地实现这些算法
and that comment was really meant only for the experts in statistics.
刚才插入的那些内容也不重要
Finally, in order to
最后
wrap this up, let me
做一个总结
take this expression and write it a little bit more compactly.
让我把这些式子写得紧凑点
So, we're going to
我可以把这个式子
write this is a product
写成一个乘积式
from J equals one
从 j=1 到 j=n
through N, of P
of XJ parameterized by
被muj和( ∑2 )^2
mu j comma sigma squared
乘积项是 p(xj; μj,  (σj)^2)
j. So this funny
在这里
symbol here, there is
出现了一个有趣的符号
capital Greek alphabet pi,
希腊字母 π
that funny symbol there corresponds to
这个有趣的字母表示的是
taking the product of a set of values.
一系列数值的乘积
And so, you're familiar with
同时
the summation notation, so the
你应该对求和符号比较熟悉
sum from i equals one through
从 i=1 到 n 求和
n, of i. This
也就是
means 1 + 2 + 3 plus
1+2+3+...
dot dot dot, up to
直到加到 n
n. Where as this
正如刚才的符号 π
funny symbol here, this product
这个求和符号 ∑
symbol, right product from i
只是表示从 i 等于1
equals 1 through n
到 n 进行连加
of i.  Then this
那么
means that, it's just like summation except that we're now multiplying.
这里的 π 也是一样 只不过表示连乘而不是连加
This becomes 1 times
这就变成了
2 times 3 times up
1×2×3 一直乘到 n
to N. And so using
所以这里用的就是
this product notation, this
这里连乘的符号
product from j equals 1 through n of this expression.
这个表达式表示从等于 j=1 开始一直乘到 j=n
It's just more compact, it's
这样写看起来更紧凑
just shorter way for writing
这样写只是避免了
out this product of
把这个乘积表达式
of all of these terms up there.
的所有项都写出来而已
Since we're are taking these p
因为我们是采用
of x j given mu j
给出mu j、∑( j )的p和xj
comma sigma squared j terms
以及
and multiplying them together.
和它们的乘积项
And, by the way the problem
同时 顺便要说的是
of estimating this distribution
估计x及p的分布的问题
p of x, they're sometimes called
这种问题通常被称为
the problem of density estimation.
密度估计问题
Hence the title of the slide.
正如幻灯片的标题上写的
So putting everything together, here
把所有的整合到一起
is our anomaly detection algorithm.
下面便是我们的异常检测算法
The first step is to choose
第一步便是选择特征
features, or come up with
或者是提出一些
features xi that we think
我们认为其指数比较反常的样本
might be indicative of anomalous examples.
的特征Xi
So what I mean by that,
因此 我的意思是
is, try to come
可以尝试着
up with features, so that when there's
提出一些特征
an unusual user in your
通过某些
system that may be doing
在你的系统里的不同学寻常的用户
fraudulent things, or when the
的反常和欺诈行为
aircraft engine examples, you know
或者是那个飞机引擎的例子
there's something funny, something strange about one of the aircraft engines.
在飞机的众多引擎里有一个奇怪的引擎
Choose features X I, that
选择特征Xi
you think might take on unusually
这个特征可能会
large values, or unusually
呈现一个不同寻常特别大的数值
small values, for what an
或者特别小的数值
anomalous example might look like.
因为这个看起来本身就有些异常
But more generally, just try
但更为普遍的是
to choose features that describe general
尽可能尝试选择用来
properties of the things that you're collecting data on.
描述这些收集的数据相关的属性的事情
Next, given a training set,
下一步是给出训练集
of M, unlabled examples,
以及没有标记的样本
X1 through X M, we
从X1到X
then fit the parameters,
我们从mu1到mun
mu 1 through mu n, and
找出里面合适的参数
sigma squared 1 through sigma
从σ1的平方到σn的平方
squared n, and so these
同时
were the formulas similar to
这些公式
the formulas we have
和之前在视频里的
in the previous video, that we're
公式比较相似
going to use the estimate
因此 我们便可以
each of these parameters, and just to give
估计这些参数的值
some interpretation, mu J,
同时 给出对应的解释
that's my average value of the j feature.
muJ是特征j的平均值
Mu j goes in this term p of xj.
muj便在xj的p这项里面
which is parametrized by mu J
被muJ
and sigma squared J. And
σJ的平方参数化
so this says for the
因此
mu J just take the
这对muJ就好比
mean over my training
通过特征j的
set of the values of the j feature.
训练集数据取平均值
And, just to mention, that you
同时
do this, you compute these
计算这些公式从
formulas for j equals
j的值从1到n
one through n. So use
然后
these formulas to estimate mu
用这些公式来估计mu1
1, to estimate mu
再估计mu2
2, and so on up to
直到mun
mu n, and similarly for sigma
同样地 对于σ的平方
squared, and it's also
同时
possible to come up with vectorized versions of these.
对于矢量化的参数特征也可能适用该方法
So if you think of
如果
mu as a vector, so mu
你把mu假想成一个向量
if is a vector there's mu 1,
那么向量mu就有
mu 2, down to mu
mu1到mu2直到mun
n, then a vectorized
那么
version of that set
向量化的参数集合
of parameters can be written
就能被写出来
like so sum from 1
其和值
equals one through n xi.
xi的值从1到n
So, this formula that I
在这个公式中
just wrote out estimates this
我刚刚写出用来估计xi值
xi as the feature vectors
的特征向量
that estimates mu for all the values of n simultaneously.
同时 对不同n的取值 这些向量也可以估计出mu的值来
And it's also possible to come
由此 提出一种
up with a vectorized formula for
针对估计σj的平方的值的
estimating sigma squared j. Finally,
矢量化的公式成为可能
when you're given a new example, so
最后 我们给出一个新案例
when you have a new aircraft engine
当有一个全新的飞机引擎时
and you want to know is this aircraft engine anomalous.
你想要知道这个飞机引擎是否出现异常
What we need to do is then
我们要做的就是
compute p of x, what's the probability of this new example?
计算出x的p值来 那么这个案例中的概率是多少呢
So, p of x is equal
我们知道x的p值
to this product, and
等于这个乘上
what you implement, what you compute,
你现在
is this formula and
正在计算的这个公式
where over here, this thing
就是这个
here this is just the
在这里的这个公式
formula for the Gaussian
是针对计算高斯概率的
probability, so you compute
计算出这一项
this thing, and finally if
最后
this probability is very small,
如果这个概率值很小
then you flag this thing as an anomaly.
那么你就将这一项标注为异常
Here's an example of an application of this method.
这就是我们应用这种方法的一个案例
Let's say we have this data
下面就让我们谈谈
set plotted on the upper left of this slide.
在幻灯片左侧上面绘制的数据集
if you look at this, well, lets look the feature of x1.
如果你看到这个 让我们看这个x1的特征
If you look at this data set, it
囚你看到这个数据集
looks like on average, the features
它看起来比较平均
x1 has a mean of about 5
x1的特征里有一个5个元素的平均值
and the standard deviation, if
并且也有一个标准差
you only look at just the x1
如果你看到了
values of this data set
x1数据集的值
has the standard deviation of maybe 2.
其标准差可能为2
So that sigma 1 and
所以对于σ1
looks like x2 the
以及看起来像
values of the features as
从纵轴测量的
measured on the vertical axis,
特征值x2
looks like it has an average
看起来其平均值
value of about 3, and
可能是3
a standard deviation of about 1. So if
且其标准差值为1
you take this data set and if
如果你使用这个数据集
you estimate mu1, mu2, sigma1,
且如果你估计mu1、mu2、σ1、
sigma2, this is what you get.
σ2 这就是你要求解的
And again, I'm writing sigma here,
再次说明一下 我在这里写的σ
I'm think about standard deviations, but
我在思考关于它的标准差
the formula on the previous 5
但先前用公式算出来是5
actually gave the estimates of the squares
实际上可以将这些项平方再进行计算
of theses things, so sigma squared 1 and sigma squared 2.
这样可得到σ1的平方以及σ2的平方
So, just be careful whether
但是你应该仔细
you are using sigma 1, sigma
你现在是否在使用σ1、
2, or sigma squared 1 or sigma squared 2.
σ2以及期其它的σ的平方项
So, sigma squared 1 of course
所以
would be equal to 4, for
σ1的平方的值当然等于4
example, as the square of 2.
举个例子 2的平方
And in pictures what p of
在图上
x1 parametrized by mu1 and
被mu1和σ1的平方以及x2的p值
sigma squared 1 and p
参数化的x1的p
of x2, parametrized by mu
被参数化的mu2
2 and sigma squared 2, that
和σ2的平方
would look like these two distributions over here.
看起来像在这里的两个分布
And, turns out that
其实是
if were to plot of p
如果绘制x的p的图像
of x, right, which
那么就会看到
is the product of these two
是这两个的乘积
things, you can actually get
事实上
a surface plot that looks like this.
你已经得到了一个这样的的表面图像
This is a plot of p
这是
of x, where the height
x的p值的图像
above of this, where the
其高度比这个高
height of this surface at
这个面的高度
a particular point, so given a
在一个特别的点上
particular x1 x2
给出一个特别的X1和X2的值
values of x2 if
如果
x1 equals 2, x equal 2, that's this point.
x1等于2 x等于2 那么就是这个点
And the height of this 3-D
在此处的的3-D表面图
surface here, that's p
那里是x的p值
of x. So p of x, that is the height
是这个图的高度
of this plot, is
从表面上看
literally just p of x1
这个x1的p值是高度
parametrized by mu 1 sigma
同时x1被mu1
squared 1, times p
σ1的平方
of x2 parametrized by
乘x2的p值
mu 2 sigma squared 2.
被mu2以及σ2的平方参数化
Now, so this is
现在
how we fit the parameters to this data.
我们便得到了这组数据的合适的参数值
Let's see if we have a couple of new examples.
让我们看看我们是否有了很多新的案例
Maybe I have a new example there.
或许在这里我们有了一个新案例
Is this an anomaly or not?
这个案例是否异常
Or, maybe I have a different
或许我现在有了一个与以往不同的案例
example, maybe I have a different second example over there.
或许在这里也有了一个与先前不同的第二案例
So, is that an anomaly or not?
那是否有异常呢?
They way we do that is, we
我们可以这么做
would set some value for
我们给计算机无穷小量设置某个数值
Epsilon, let's say I've chosen
我设置的
Epsilon equals 0.02.
计算机无穷小量数值为0.02
I'll say later how we choose Epsilon.
我会在后面讲到如何选取无穷小量的数值
But let's take this first
不过 我们先讲这个第一个案例
example, let me call this
让我把这个称为
example X1 test.
案例X1测试
And let me call the second example
同时
X2 test.
称第二个案例为X2测试
What we do is, we
我们现在要做的
then compute p of
就是把X1测试中的的p值计算出来
X1 test, so we use
之后
this formula to compute it and
观察用这个公式计算出来数值
this looks like a pretty large value.
不难发现这是一个相当大的数
In particular, this is greater
特别地 这个值可能大于
than, or greater than or equal to epsilon.
或者大于等于计算机的无穷小量
And so this is a pretty
但其实相较于计算机的无穷小量
high probability at least bigger
这个数值还是比较大的
than epsilon, so we'll say that
所以我们也说
X1 test is not an anomaly.
X1检测的结果不是异常
Whereas, if you compute p of
然而 如果你计算x2检测的p值
X2 test, well that is just a much smaller value.
会是一个更加小的数
So this is less than
比计算机的无穷小量还要小
epsilon and so we'll say
同时我们也会说
that that is indeed an anomaly,
那确实是一个异常数值
because it is much smaller than that epsilon that we then chose.
因为那已经远远小于了先前我们定义的计算机无穷小量的值
And in fact, I'd improve it here.
但事实上 我们也可以对这个方法进行改良
What this is really saying is that, you look through the 3d surface plot.
看这个三维表面图
It's saying that all the
从图上不难看出
values of x1 and x2
x1和x2的所有数值
that have a high height
所在位置都是比较高的
above the surface, corresponds to
尤其是
an a non-anomalous example of an OK or normal example.
和一个比较好的或者一个正常案例比起来
Whereas all the points far out
然而所有的点
here, all the points out
距离这里都比较远
here, all of those
所有的这些点
points have very low
其概率值都比较小
probability, so we are
所以
going to flag those points
我们会把这些点标注成异常
as anomalous, and so it's gonna define
并依此定义一些区域
some region, that maybe looks
那么这么做之后 看起来可能是这样
like this, so that everything
那些
outside this, it flags
在这之外的
as anomalous,
被标注成为异常
whereas the things inside this
然后在里面的
ellipse I just drew, if it
这个我刚画的椭圆形的这个
considers okay, or non-anomalous, not anomalous examples.
如果它被认为是正常的 也可以说是非异常的案例
And so this example x2
案例X2
test lies outside
位于
that region, and so it
那个区域之外
has very small probability, and so we consider it an anomalous example.
那就有一个很小的概率 并且我们认为它是一个异常的案例
In this video we talked about how to
在本节视频中
estimate p of x, the probability of
我们谈到了如何估计x的p值
x, for the purpose of
x的概率值
developing an anomaly detection algorithm.
以开发出一种异常检测的算法
And in this video, we also
在本节视频中
stepped through an entire process
我们使用给出的数据集
of giving data set, we
将整个操作流程都一步步走了下来
have, fitting the parameters, doing parameter estimations.
我们找到了和合适的参数值并得到了估计的参数值
We get mu and sigma parameters, and
我们得到了mu和σ的参数
then taking new examples and deciding
然后对这些新的案例进行使用
if the new examples are anomalous or not.
判断这些新的案例是不是有异常
In the next few videos we
在接下来的几段视频中
will delve deeper into this algorithm,
我们将更加深入地挖掘这个算法的内含
and talk a bit more
此外
about how to actually get this to work well.
我们也会说道如何更好地将这个算法投入实际的生产和工作中